Young people that have got, kind of,
good like I say, strong family links,
strong friendships, also young people
that are involved in their community.
So young people that may like a club.
So they might be in Scouts.
They might be Guides.
They might be in dancing.
They might be in football.
They might be links to the community.
So they've got, kind of,
stuff to do outside of school.
They're like quite strong protective
factors for young people because
they've got stuff on, you know, outside.
So they've got the family they've
got their friends, they've got
their hobbies you've got, kind of
stuff that they're sharing as well.
And also they've got good
relationships with school as well.
'Cause I think, I think school is
really key for young people because
you know they're there most of the
time at this age and I think a lot
of young people who come through us.
There's always like, they always say
they've got like one or two people
at school who they can talk to.
And that to me is a good protective
factor because there's that key person
at school, who they can talk to.
They go into, like, say
dancing after school, they've
got good friendship groups.
These are all protective factors because
as well also, they're not involved with
kind of substance misuse or not involved
with any kind of antisocial behavior.
'Cause I think obviously they're the
ones, that's the kind of area, which kind
of moves young people to the other side.
So I think young people that've stayed
away from kind of harmful behavior, like
substance misuse and antisocial behavior,
the strong links with their friends and
family they're involved in the community,
they're attending school, they've also
got links, good links with the school.
And they've also got aspirations
of what they want to do as well.
'Cause I think, you know, a lot of
young people you talk to now, they
kind of, some people know what they
want to do, like, I've worked with a
lot young people recenty they said,
"oh, after school, I'm going to college
and I'm going to do uniform services".
One of them was saying, "oh,
after college, I'm going to...
I want to do social care because
of the background that I've had".
Or, you know, young people have got kind
of some, you know, they have a direction.
And to me, that's very protective because
they've got aspirations, you've got
goals and that's something we do here in
people as well when we start working with
him, we give him like, say three, have
they got three goals that you want to
achieve in the time that we work with you?
If they've got goals and they've
got aspirations, then they're less
likely to kind of get involved
with the substance misuse.
So maybe CSE stuff, the risky
behavior stuff, because they've
got the strong, protective factors.